<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Catholique doctor and his spiritual catholicon to cure our sinfull soules a communion-sermon preach'd to the Right Honourable Sr. Robert Foster Lord Chief Justice of the King's bench, and the rest of the reverend judges, and serjeants at law, in Serjeants-Inn in Fleetstreet, on Sunday May the 26th, 1661 / by Matthevv Griffith ...</title>
            <author>Griffith, Matthew, 1599?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42149</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G2010</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12781716</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12781716</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93824</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42149)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93824)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 983:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Catholique doctor and his spiritual catholicon to cure our sinfull soules a communion-sermon preach'd to the Right Honourable Sr. Robert Foster Lord Chief Justice of the King's bench, and the rest of the reverend judges, and serjeants at law, in Serjeants-Inn in Fleetstreet, on Sunday May the 26th, 1661 / by Matthevv Griffith ...</title>
                  <author>Griffith, Matthew, 1599?-1665.</author>
                  <author>Foster, Robert, Sir, 1589-1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Godbid for John Playford ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Communion sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93824:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93824:1"/>
            <p>THE Catholique Doctor AND HIS SPIRITUAL CATHOLICON To CURE Our SINFULL SOULES.</p>
            <p>A COMMUNION-SERMON Preach'd to the Right Honourable S<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>ROBERT FOSTER</hi> Lord Chief Juſtice of the KINGS BENCH, and the reſt of the Reverend Judges, and Serjeants at LAW, in <hi>SERJEANTS-Inne</hi> in <hi>Fleetſtreet,</hi> On Sunday <hi>May</hi> the 26th. 1661.</p>
            <p>BY MATTHEVV GRIFFITH, D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. Godbid</hi> for <hi>John Playford</hi> in the <hi>Inner Temple.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:93824:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:93824:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable EDVVARD EARL of <hi>CLARENDON</hi> Lord Chancellour of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T may ſeem a Paradox, though it be true, that this Communion Sermon was preach'd in a ſmall Congregation, <hi>viz.</hi> the Chappel in <hi>Serjeants-Inne</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet;</hi> yet to a great and grave Auditory, for the reverend Judges, and Serjeants at Law, were pleas'd there to honour me with their attention and approbation. And as it is the onely ſtaffe of my age, and cheif comfort of my life, that I am a ſervant to the truely Honorable Societies of the <hi>Temple,</hi> of which the ſaid Judges and Serjeants not long ſince were a conſiderable part: ſo that I might not die altogether a ſtranger to your Lordſhip (whom all knowing men look upon as the Quinteſſence, and higheſt Extraction of thoſe noble Societies) I have aſſumed the confidence (being over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entreated to print this Sermon) to recommend herein
<pb facs="tcp:93824:3"/> to your Lordſhip a Phyſician, in whoſe care and cuſtody you may ſafely venture both body and ſoul; in which reſpect as he is every way worthy of your Lordſhips cordial entertainment: ſo my hope is that Your accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed goodneſs will not onely pardon this preſumption in one, whoſe yet ſuffering condition can give no better evidence, and aſſurance of his reall reverence, and ſincere deſire to ſerve Your Lordſhip: but alſo freely permit him to publiſh this peice of devotion under your Lordſhips name unto the people: for your native Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, and ſupernatural Clemency, have made you (as the Hiſtorian ſtiles <hi>Titus</hi>) their darling and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light: Among whom not onely your Lordſhips counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, but connivance is enough to candy any perſon, or action; and to gain them both authority and acceptation. Your Lordſhips infallible prudence in counſelling, and irreſiſtible power in perſwading out-ſhine all humane preſidents; and whoſoever would now advance himſelf like an Oratour, he muſt firſt ſit a while in ſilence at Your Lordſhips feet, and learn of you (who are onely able) to ſpeak with as much grace, and gravity, as both <hi>Neſtor,</hi> and <hi>Gamaliel.</hi> His Sacred Majeſty (who is under God the fountain of honour) could not poſſibly do himſelf more right, then by advancing you; who are obſerv'd to diſcharge the high and weighty place of <hi>Lord Chancellour,</hi> with ſo much ability, and ſatisfaction, that the Dignity it ſelf is preferr'd in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conferr'd upon Your Lordſhip; all whoſe Injunctions, and Decrees, are temper'd not onely <hi>Ad Juſtitiam,</hi> but <hi>Ad pondus aequale:</hi> ſo that though but one ſide can prevaile, yet the other hath not the leaſt colour to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain
<pb facs="tcp:93824:3"/> of any thing but the demerits of his Cauſe. And howe're the incredible extent, and irreparable expence of ſome Suites in Chancery have formerly turn'd both parts into Plaintiffs at laſt, when though one ſeem'd to get the better, yet in truth both were worſted: yet now Your Lordſhips integrity and dexterity in determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning cauſes, render all Commencers in that Honorable Court, as happy as any that go to Law (which is a kind of waging war) can in reaſon hope to be, <hi>Cita mors, aut Victoria laeta.</hi> We need no other argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to prove, or inducements to believe, that His Sacred Majeſty hath at this day that extraordinary gift, which the Apoſtle call'd, <hi>The Spirit of diſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning;</hi> but onely this, that he ſingled out Your Lordſhip as One fit, and worthy to be neareſt Himſelf. If <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> in his time had been bleſs'd with ſuch a Counſellor, ſure <hi>Jethro</hi> would never have diminiſh'd his Greatneſs by Adviſing him to call in ſo many Aſſiſtants. Your Lordſhips wiſdome is ſole-ſufficient to govern the vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Empire; which irrefragable truth no man can deny without the guilt and cenſure of groſs ignorance, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, and hereſie. And were we not generally ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, if not ſtupid, we would profeſſedly congratulate our own happineſs in the accumulation of your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours; and wiſh them in all reſpects as tranſcendent as your Merits. But though ſome others, (like the nine Leapers that were heal'd) return not thanks, yet for my part the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> hath taught me to ſay, Good luck have you with your Honour: Ride on, till your chriſtian progreſs centre in perfection: in order where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto you carry your ſelf with ſo much ſobriety, and
<pb facs="tcp:93824:4"/> ſweetneſs, that thoſe few who maligne your fortune, yet cannot but love your perſon; and all the reſt think it their happineſs to be commanded by your Lordſhip. In whom (as it is ſaid of <hi>Daniel 5. 14.</hi>) the Spirit of the Holy Gods, light, and underſtanding, and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent wiſdome is found: and conſequently your Lordſhip deſerves that Eulogie in the <hi>North,</hi> which the Queen of the <hi>South</hi> gave to <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf; Happy are thy ſervants that ſtand alwayes in thy preſence to hear thy wiſdome: This is all the ambition of him, who here in all humility craves your Lordſhips patronage, and vow's himſelf</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The humbleſt of Your Lordſhips Servants, and trueſt Honourers, <hi>Matthew Griffith.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:93824:4"/>
            <head>The <hi>CATHOLIQUE DOCTOR</hi> AND His SPIRIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AL CATHOLICON TO Cure Our <hi>SINFULL SOULES.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>1 JOHN 1. 7.</bibl>
               <q>The Blood of Jeſus Chriſt, his Son, cleanſeth us from all Sin.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE ſum of all knowledge is Divinity, the ſum of all Divinity is the Scripture; the ſum of all the Scripture is the Goſpel; the ſum of all the Goſpel is my Text; and the ſum of my Text is in the Verbe, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Cleanſeth;</hi> which Verbe is a Metaphor taken from the learned, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary profeſſion of Phyſick, in which there be ſo many ſorts of purging and cleanſing medicines.</p>
            <p>And (if you will give me leave to follow this Metaphor in dividing my Text) it will fairely, and without the leaſt ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, lead your Chriſtian devotion into the ſerious conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</p>
            <p>Firſt of a Phyſician, who is here deſcrib'd not onely by his proper name, <hi>Ieſus;</hi> and his Appellative name, <hi>Chriſt;</hi> but alſo by ſomewhat that is Relative, <hi>His Son; viz.</hi> The Son of God, ſpoken of in the Context,</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:93824:5"/>
            <p>Secondly, Of the Phyſick here adminiſtr'd, <hi>viz. Blood: The Blood of Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Of the Operation of this <hi>Blood,</hi> which is the Phyſick in the Text, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>It cleanſeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, Of the Patients on whom this Phyſick works, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, Of the ſickneſs which ſo much endangers us, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly, Of the Extent of this mortal diſeaſe, inſinuated in the Collective, <hi>All, all Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the firſt you may note the tranſcendent diginity of this Phyſician; for it is neither <hi>Galen,</hi> nor <hi>Hipocrates,</hi> nor any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meer man; nor <hi>Aeſculapius, Apollo,</hi> or any fictitious Diety; nor <hi>Menecrates</hi> who affected to be ſtiled <hi>Menecrates Jupiter:</hi> but it is Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond note the excellency of this Phyſick, for it is no ordinary <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſimple, or <hi>Indian</hi> drugge; but it is blood; and not any blood neither, as the blood of the Levitical Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices; but by way of ſingularity, it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The blood; even the blood of the Phyſician himſelf; The blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt his Son.</p>
            <p>In the third note the admirable efficacy, and operation of this blood; for it is not onely <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but alſo <hi>Catholicon,</hi> an Univerſal cleanſer.</p>
            <p>In the fourth note the extreme miſery of mankind ſince the fall, expreſs'd in the parable of the wounded Travailer: and here implied in this <hi>Us,</hi> which I properly call The Patient.</p>
            <p>In the fifth Note the extraordinary malignity of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorable, and almoſt deſperate malady, which is here call'd <hi>Sin.</hi> For this <hi>Sin</hi> is ſuch a ſickneſs as can not poſſibly be cur'd by any other meanes, then <hi>Blood;</hi> nor by any other <hi>blood,</hi> then that of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> the Phyſician in the Text.</p>
            <p>In the ſixt and laſt, Note the vaſt extent, and latitude of this diſeaſe; expreſs'd in this Collective, <hi>All;</hi> and ſo St. <hi>John</hi>'s meaning is to aſſure us for our comfort <hi>that the blood of Chriſt cures all our ſickneſs,</hi> when he ſaith here, <hi>that it cleanſeth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:93824:5"/> us from all Sin.</hi> Theſe ſix are the parts; of all which in this order with ſo much brevity, as can any way ſtand with per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuity: and I begin with him, who deſerves to be our firſt conſideration, <hi>viz. Jeſus Chriſt, his Son.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Of whom that I may ſpeak more diſtinctly, let your attenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, intention, and retention, keep pace with me through theſe two conſiderations: The one is of our Saviours Perſon; and the other of his Profeſſion, which in the regular proſecution of this allegory continued in the Text, I call A Phyſician. Again in opening the former conſideration, <hi>viz.</hi> that of our Saviours Perſon, I ſhall take juſt occaſion to ſpeak ſomewhat both of his names, <hi>Jeſus, Chriſt:</hi> and alſo of his natures; the divine, and the humane; one of which is clearly expreſs'd, and the other neceſſarily implied in theſe two tearmes; <hi>His Son.</hi> A word of each; and firſt of his proper name, <hi>Jeſus;</hi> This ſignifies a Saviour, it is a broken Hebrew word, (as Criticks obſerve) and it is our Phyſicians proper name; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it is not improper for any Phyſician to be ſtil'd a Saviour, becauſe his principal aim and end is to ſave his Patients, that is, to keep them ſafe and ſound; ſo that by the help and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Phyſick, They may have what all men do, or ſhould pray, and labour for, <hi>viz. Mentem ſanam in corpore ſano.</hi> But the Phyſician in my Text is a Saviour <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; for at the very impoſition of his name, the Angel (<hi>Matth.</hi> 1. 21.) made this the Expoſition of the ſame, <hi>Thou ſhalt call his name Jeſus; for he ſhall ſave his people from their ſins.</hi> Then a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician he was, yet with this difference; Other Phyſicians cure our bodies, He our Souls; they our ſickneſs, He our Sins. This Jeſus was a Saviour; yet not like <hi>Joſeph, Joſua, Jepthah; Gedeon, Othoniel,</hi> and ſome others, who in Scripture are call'd Saviours, too, in their kind; but they were onely typical, and temporary Saviours; they ſaved the people among whom they lived, onely from temporal evils, and enemies: but this <hi>Jeſus</hi> was the truth of all thoſe types; and juſtified to be a Saviour under Gods broad Seal; as having power thereby to ſave his people both from Sin, the root; and miſeries, the branches; from death, I mean eternal, which St. <hi>John</hi> calls
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93824:6"/> the ſecond death; and the Devil, who is ſaid to have the power of death; and the curſe of the Law, and the wrath of God; from all which none could ſave us, but this <hi>Jeſus</hi> in the Text. Of which ſweet and ſaving name St. <hi>Bernard</hi> deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants thus, <hi>Nomen Ieſu lux, cibus, medicina eſt:</hi> The name Jeſus is both our light, our meat, and our medicine: <hi>lucet praedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>paſcit recogitatum, ſanat invocatum.</hi> And elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where in his devotions he calls this <hi>Jeſus Mel in ore, melos in aure, jubilus in corde.</hi> This Jeſus (ſay others) is the ſick mans ſalve, and the Souldiers ſheild, he ſolaceth the Patient, and ſupports the deficient, and encourageth the proficient, and crownes the perſeverant.</p>
               <p>I may call this name <hi>Jeſus,</hi> Angelical; for (in the ſecond Chapter of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> at the twenty firſt verſe) I find him call'd <hi>Ieſus</hi> by the Angel, before he was conceived in the womb. His name <hi>Chriſt</hi> is prophetical; for the Prophets ſtill call him in Hebrew, <hi>The Meſsias;</hi> which in Greek ſignifies <hi>The Chriſt,</hi> And if, with St. <hi>John</hi> in the Text, we put the two names together, then we have his name Evangelical: for <hi>(Iohn 20. 31.) Theſe things were written, that you might believe that Ieſus is the Chriſt, the Son of God, and that believing you might have life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He is <hi>Jeſus</hi> in Hebrew, to ſhew that he is a Saviour to the Jews; and he is call'd <hi>Chriſt</hi> in Greek, to ſhew that he is a Saviour to the Gentiles alſo: And both theſe names are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly given him in holy writ, to ſhew that he is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Saviour of both: and St. <hi>Iohn</hi> hath coupled them in the Text, to ſignifie that the wall of ſeparation is now broken down, and ſo no difference between his Patients; as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle (<hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 28.) ſpeaks plainly, <hi>There is neither Iew nor Greek, neither bond nor free, neither male or female; for ye are all one in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt ſignifies Annointed; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>nomen verbale a</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>ungo,</hi> ſay Criticks. And this which I call his Appellative, ſhews him to be a Phyſician, too: for he was Annointed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf that he might annoint us: yea he was annointed the rather that he might as a Phyſician be the more ſucceſsful; which I
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93824:6"/> take to be the meaning of that prophecy in the 61 chap. of <hi>Iſaiah;</hi> which our Saviour applies to himſelf in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> chap. of St. <hi>Luke, The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, therefore hath the Lord annointed me; he hath ſent me to preach good tydings to the poor, to bind up the broken hearted, &amp;c.</hi> Never ſuch a Phyſician as this; none can binde up, and heal the broken hearted, but He: never ſuch Phyſick as this <hi>Blood</hi> in the Text, which he adminiſtred onely as he was annointed. Yea he is not onely Annointed in himſelf, but he is our Ointment too; in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Chapter of the firſt Epiſtle of St. <hi>John,</hi> at the twenty ſeventh Verſe; and ſuch annointment as is tranſient from him, and immanent in us; for that ointment which you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from him, as Chriſtians, dwells in you, ſaith St. <hi>John:</hi> and this inhabitation makes you to be, as well as to be call'd, Chriſtians. And as the precious ointment which was poured on <hi>Aarons</hi> head, ran down his beard, ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> and thence to the skirts of his cloathing: ſo Chriſt was not ſo much annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for himſelf, who is the head of all principalities and powers, ſaith the Apoſtle, and in whom dwelt the fullneſs of the Godhead, even bodily: as for us; that ſo from him as our head, the grace and vertue of his Annointing might de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcend upon us, who are ſo many real, though inferiour mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his myſtical body, or rather but the skirts of his cloathing. Briefly, The fathers out of the Scripture af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming that in him all fullneſs dwelt, enlarge themſelves thus, There was in Chriſt fullneſs of favour, fullneſs of preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, fullneſs of influence, fullneſs of grace, <hi>&amp;c. And of his fullneſs</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>John 1. 16.) we have all received, and grace for grace;</hi> grace in our proportion, though not in his perfection.</p>
               <p>Now, it is obſervable that as Kings and Prieſts in times paſt were ordinarily annointed, and the Prophet <hi>Elizeus</hi> extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily: So in this Chriſt all theſe Three Offices met. For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, A Prieſt he was, and a Prieſt for ever after the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Melchizedek,</hi> in the 110. Pſalm, at the the 4. Verſe. <hi>I have ſworn, and will not repent, thou art a Preiſt for ever, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the order of Melchizedek.</hi> Not after the Order of <hi>Aaron;</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:93824:7"/> for his Prieſthood was Levitical and Typical; and ſo ceas'd when the Fullneſſe of time was come: but after the Order of <hi>Melchizedek;</hi> who was both King of <hi>Salem (Heb.</hi> 7. 1.) and alſo Prieſt of the moſt High God? Yea he was the true <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedek;</hi> without Father as he was Man; without Mother as he was God.</p>
               <p>Secondly, A Prophet he was; and that Prophet which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaks of (<hi>Deut. 18. 18.) A Prophet ſhall the Lord your God raiſe up unto you from among your Brethren, like unto me.</hi> And though in ſome things Chriſt was but like to <hi>Moſes,</hi> yet in moſt things he excell'd even <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelf, who might have juſtly ſaid as <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> doth, <hi>He that comes after meis preferred before me,</hi> Joh. 3.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, A King he was to ſave his people, <hi>Ieremiah</hi> the 23. and the 6. yea he was not only a King; but the King proclaim'd in the 9. of <hi>Zechary</hi> at the 9. Verſe. <hi>Behold the King comes to thee,</hi> &amp;c. Yea he was the King of Kings. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 19. 16. Briefly this Chriſt was <hi>Davids</hi> prieſt; and <hi>Moſes</hi> his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; and <hi>Ieremies</hi> King.</p>
               <p>Theſe Offices had formerly met double; I find two of them in ſome others: For <hi>Melchizedek</hi> was King and prieſt; <hi>Samuel</hi> was prieſt and prophet; <hi>David</hi> was prophet, and King: yet all the three never met in any one ſave this Chriſt alone; and conſequently no perfect Chriſt but he; but he, was all, and ſo all-perfect. Yea he was not only a Chriſt, but even <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>The Chriſt,</hi> for ſo the Tearm is both propounded and expounded (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 1. 22.) we have found the <hi>Meſſias,</hi> which is by Interpretation, <hi>The Chriſt,</hi> not only <hi>Chriſtus Domini</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) but even <hi>Chriſtus Dominus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus having opened his two names, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> I come now to touch with a light pencil his two natures; the one implyed, the other expreſſed in the two next words, <hi>His Son. The Blood of Ieſus Chriſt his Son,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>This Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God; yet his Son he is, neither by creation as are the Angels of Heaven; nor yet by adoption, as are the Saints on Earth, but by Generation; for ſo ſaith God by his prophet (<hi>Pſal. 2. 7.) Thou art my Son,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93824:7"/> this day have I begotten thee? Thee</hi> including Chriſt: and ſo much the apoſtolick Writer in his firſt Chapter to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> at the Fifth Verſe, applies unto Chriſt <hi>Antonomaſtice,</hi> exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Creatures; for <hi>to which of them ſaid God at any time, Thou art my Son,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>And this Jeſus Chriſt doth ordinarily in the Goſpel ſtyle himſelf, <hi>The Son of man:</hi> So that there were two Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in him, The Divine and the Humane; and he was one of both Natures, not two in both: One and the ſame with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out time, begotten of the Father, the Son of God without Mother, and in time begotten of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> the Son of Man without Father; the true, natural, real and conſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Son of both. Thus was he the Son of God, and Man; yet not by confuſion of Subſtance but by Unity of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And this Union of the Divine and Humane nature in him, is called by the Schoolmen a Perſonal Conjunction, yet not of perſons; and it is of two Natures, yet not natural: for as The Word becauſe of the Fleſh is man, ſo the Fleſh becauſe of the Word is God; and yet neither is the humane Nature coextended with the Divine, nor the Divine nature concluded in the humane.</p>
               <p>In the creation we read that God made man like himſelf, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 26. but in the Redemption it is plain, that God made himſelf like man: and as at firſt man was like God in nothing but Holineſſe; (for ſo the Apoſtle (<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 24.) expounds Gods Image) ſo at laſt God was like man in all things but Sin: He became that which he was not, yet ſtill remained that which he was; being at one and the ſame time both perfect in his own nature, and true in ours: That there might be as great Humility in the Redeemer, as there was pride in the <hi>Praevaricatour;</hi> and as there was at firſt ſo great pride, that Man would be as God. <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 6. So there was at laſt ſo great Humility, that God would become man; even of a reaſonable Soul, and humane fleſh ſubſiſting; as in the Athanaſian Creed. Thus he that was the Son of God from everlaſting, was born in the fulneſſe of time, as the Son of man; and he that was born as the Son of man, wrought
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93824:8"/> miracles as the Son of God; and he that wrought miracles as the Son of God, dyed as the Son of man; and he that died as the Son of man, roſe again from the dead as he was the Son of God.</p>
               <p>O wonder at this, all you that wonder at nothing elſe; for this is admirably ſingular, and ſingularly to be admired: This was ſuch a work, ſuch a wonder; that I muſt needs ſay (with St. <hi>Hierome</hi>) that which nature had not, which uſe knew not, which reaſon was ignorant of, which the minde of man was uncapable of, which the Angels themſelves (till reveal'd) underſtood not; and which all the powers of created na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtood amaz'd at, came to paſs, when the Son of God in the Text became the Son of man; taking the divine and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane nature into the unity of his perſon, that ſo he might bring God and man into the unity of affection.</p>
               <p>It is confeſs'd that only the humane nature that Sin'd, ought to have made ſatisfaction, but that alone could not; for by Sin an infinite Majeſty was offended, and therefore infinite ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction was to be made; but meer man being a finite creature could not poſſibly make infinite ſatisfaction: and it cannot be denied but that the Divine nature could have ſatisfied, and that alone for Sin, but that alone ought not; for man had Sin'd, and therefore man muſt ſuffer: Now, in this Jeſus Chriſt both theſe natures met; for he was the Son both of God, and man; and as he was the Son of man, he was truely liable to the debt of Sin; and as he was the Son of God, he was fully able to diſcharge it: and ſo as the Son of man, he ſuffer'd; as he was the Son of God, he ſatisfied; and as he was the Son of both, he ſaved us.</p>
               <p>And thus having ſhewed his Perſon; I ſtand now bound by a debt of promiſe to ſpeak ſomewhat of his Profeſſion; for if we look upon the words of my Text, as a continued alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory, as you may remember we did when we took it in peices; then this <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> as he is the Son of God and man in the Text, doth perſonate a Phyſician; and indeed whilſt he was incarnate, he ſeem'd to delight in no one title more then this of a Phyſician; as you may obſerve both in the ninth Chapter
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93824:8"/> of St. <hi>Matth.</hi> at the twelfth Verſe: where (apologizing for his frequenting the company of publicans, and ſinners) he doth it under this parable, <hi>The whole have no need of the Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, but the ſick.</hi> His meaning was, that as Sin is a ſickneſs, ſo he was a Phyſician; and as Phyſicians for the moſt part are taken up in viſiting their patients, ſo was he: and as the ſound need not the Phyſician, ſo the Phariſees, who were ſo many Juſticiaries, and truſted in their own righteouſneſs, never thought that they ſtood in need of Chriſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And alſo in the fourth Chap. of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> at the 23<hi rend="sup">d</hi>., Verſe, ye will ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, according to the proverb, <hi>Phyſician heal thy ſelf.</hi> In both which, and divers other places, and paſſages of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, he aſſumes the habit, and profeſſion of a Phyſician; and well he might, for as in ſome things he was like other Phyſicians; ſo in many things he did exceed, and excel them. I ſay again that in ſome things Chriſt was like other Phyſici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; for</p>
               <p>Firſt as a Phyſician muſt be thoroughly skill'd in the Theory of all Diſeaſes, that ſo he may know how to proportion, and apply his medicines to the radical humour of every malady that ill affects his patients: ſo in Chriſt were hid all the treaſures of wiſdome, and knowledge, ſaith the Apoſtle; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he could not be ignorant of the cauſe, or cure of any E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil that befalls us; he knows whereof we are made, ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt;</hi> yea all our lurking diſtempers, and ſecret ſins are naked, and open before him, whoſe eyes are a thouſand times brighter then the Sunne.</p>
               <p>Secondly, As a Phyſician carefully and compaſſionately viſits his ſick patients, and abhors not their perſons, though their diſeaſes be never ſo loathſome: ſo for us men, and for our Salvation Chriſt deſcended from the boſome of his heavenly Father into the womb of his Virgin Mother: and in the dayes of his fleſh he was ſo farre from abhorring our natural unclea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and even unnatural luſts, that he took upon him all our poenal infirmities, (as the Schoolmen ſpeak) though not our ſinful: <hi>and he was tempted in all things like unto us, ſinne onely excepted,</hi> as we read in the ſecond to the <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93824:9"/> the 17. Verſe; that ſo he might the better ſympathize in all our Sufferings, and heal our ſins.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, As it is the praiſe of a Phyſician that he will viſit the poor though they be not ſolvant, and he will not protract his cures beyond the Rules of Art, though he might thereby much enrich himſelf: So Chriſt did freely adminiſter all his Spiritual potions: and he cured all ſuch as had long languiſhed, ſpeedily: Yea, he not only heal'd all that came; but he invited them to come unto him, as in the 11. Chapter of St. <hi>Mathew</hi> and the 28. Verſe, <hi>Come unto me all ye that are weary and heavy laden, and I will refreſh you:</hi> and when they were ſo wearyed with the load of Sin, that they were not able to come unto him, he vouchſafed to come unto them; and he ſoughtout opportunities to be doing of good.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, As a Phyſician ſeldome adminiſters Phyſick, but where he finds both a capacity and velleity in the Patients to take it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo Chriſt commonly gives his ſpiritual Medicins to none but ſuch as are poor in Spirit, which makes them capable; and tonone but ſuch as <hi>hunger and thirſt after righteouſneſs,</hi> which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues an eager appetite, and velleity to become ſafe and ſound. You know how he began his cure upon the <hi>Cripple (John</hi> 5. 6.) that had layen ſo long at the Pool of <hi>Betheſda, vis ſanus fieri? wilt thou be made whole?</hi> and as ſoon as he had profeſs'd his willingneſſe, but only that he wanted a man to help him; then Chriſt as a Phyſician ſaid, and his word had a deed in it: <hi>Ecce ſanus factus es! Behold thou art made whole?</hi> and he is conſtant to this method in all his cures.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, As a Phyſician often cures by contraries, as a Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fet by Faſting, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So Chriſt by his obedience did cure our diſobedience; by his humility our pride; by his bounty our avarice, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> briefly his poverty was our riches; his death our life; his croſſe our crown. Thus, as the Apoſtle ſpeaks in the firſt Chapter of the firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> at the Thirty Verſe, <hi>Chriſt was made unto us of God, Wiſdome, Righteouſneſſe, Sanctification and redemption:</hi> That by his Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome he might cure our Folly; by his Righteouſneſſe our Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; by his Sanctification our prophaneſs; by his Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion our Spiritual bondage.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:93824:9"/>
               <p>Sixthly, As when a Phyſician hath cured his patient of a dangerous Diſeaſe, he preſcribes him a Dyet for fear of a Relapſe, which is ever dangerous and ſometimes deadly: So Chriſt when he hath converted a Sinner (which is a Spiritual Cure) he ever preſcribes him a Dyet to prevent Relapſing: as to the Cripple (in the 5. chap. of St. <hi>John</hi> verſe 14.) <hi>Behold thou art made whole: Sin no more, leaſt a worſe thing fall unto thee.</hi> In which method of our Saviour we may obſerve, firſt the commemoration of a benefit received, <hi>Behold thou art made whole.</hi> Secondly, a caution to be duely obſerved, <hi>Sin no more.</hi> Thirdly, the commination of a judgement to be avoided, <hi>leſt a worſe thing fall unto thee.</hi> As if he had ſaid; no Sin goes unpuniſhed; and what ere thou haſt ſuffered for thy former fins, yet if thou go on, a worſe thing may befall thee in this Life; and if not here, then I tremble to think on, and am altogether unwilling to prognoſticate, what (if thou dye in thy Sins) will be thy portion in the Life to come. And as in all theſe reſpects Chriſt reſembles other Phyſicians: So in divers others he exceeds and excells them all, as I come now to ſhew; For,</p>
               <p>Firſt, All other Phyſicians are fain to make uſe of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary means, ſuch as are Roots, Herbs, and Flowers in the Galenical way; and of Minerals in the Paracelſian: but this Phyſician cured moſt of his Patients only by his Word: and either he made no uſe of the means, or he wrought his cures even againſt the means, for being the firſt cauſe, the whole Series of the Creatures were ſubordinate and ſubſervient to his abſolute will and command.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Howe're other Phyſicians may cure ſome diſeaſes, yet they cannot cure all, ſome maladies being in their own nature incurable; but nothing was impoſſible to Chriſt, he could cure all Comers. And therefore St. <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> pointed at him, and painted him to the Life, with an <hi>En &amp; Ecce, Behold the Lamb of God that takes away the Sin of the World,</hi> Joh. 1. 29. Sin is the procreating cauſe of all Sickneſſe, in the Third of the <hi>Lamentations</hi> at the Thirty ninth Verſe. Man ſuffers for his Sins. And this Phyſician taking away the cauſe, the cure muſt needs follow.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:93824:10"/>
               <p>Thirdly, Though other phyſicians may ſometimes be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental to haſten health, yet never could any of them prevent death; <hi>Contra vim mortis non eſt medicamen in hortis.</hi> Their Cure is at moſt but a Reprieve, no Goal-Delivery, <hi>Interdum medica plus valet arte malum;</hi> but this Phyſician in the Text, is not only <hi>Morbifugus,</hi> but alſo <hi>Mortifugus.</hi> He alone Tryumphs over Death and the Grave, as in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>O death I will be thy death! O grave I will be thy Victory!</hi> Chriſt by his Death hath both taken out, and taken away the ſting of Death; ſo that now, like a Serpent without a ſting, Deaths Malice is Toothleſſe. The Death of the Saints in Scripture is called but a diſſolution, a departure, a ſleep, a reſting in hope, till Chriſt (who is the Reſurrection, and the Life) ſhall awake them.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, Other Phyſicians can only cure our bodies, which are but one conſtituting part of man, and the worſt of the two; but Chriſt both heals and ſaves the whole man, yea all mankind, if they will take his potions, and live according to his preſcriptions; which muſt be obſerved and ſtrictly too, upon pain not only of Death but of Damnation.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, Other Phyſicians uſe Phlebotomy, and let their patient blood to cure them, but Chriſt himſelf was let blood to ſave us: So malignant and peſtilential was the burning Feaver of our ſins, that if our Phyſician had not bled to Death, we could not poſſibly have lived, either the Life of Grace on Earth, or the Life of Glory in the Heavens.</p>
               <p>And ſo I have done with the firſt main part, <hi>viz.</hi> The Phyſician, in the conſideration of whom, becauſe I have ſo enlarg'd my ſelf, I will handle all the reſt with Laconick bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>The ſecond thing conſiderable here is the Phyſick which this Phyſician adminiſters; and this ſaith St. <hi>John</hi> here, is <hi>Blood;</hi> for ſo ſtand the Words, <hi>The Blood of Jeſus, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ancient Phyſicians had an excellent Receipt, which they called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, becauſe it was a mixture of many bloods: but why was this waſt? why ſuch a mixture, and of ſo many bloods? when as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, This <hi>Blood</hi> in the Text, is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93824:10"/> and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a ſoveraign Medicine for every Malady: <hi>Nam cum me pulſat turpis aliqua cogitatio</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) when any unclean thought aſſaults me, I ſtraight recul to the wounds of my Saviour; when I ſtumble and fall foul through any ſtrong infirmity, the Meditation of my Saviours wounds raiſeth me up; yea when the Divel either openly like a roar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lyon; or privily like a ſubtile Serpent lyes in wait to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour me, I both flye to, and hide me in the holes of the Rock, my Saviours wounds, and I am ſafe. Briefly, there is none ſo catholick a remedy as the <hi>Blood of Chriſt;</hi> for this contains in it vertually all the parts of Phyſick, ſuch as are Sweatings, Vomits, Unctions, Minutions, Potions, Diets, Watchings, Exerciſes, Clyſters, Cauterizings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſpiritual Sweatings are ſharp Agonies, breathed out in briniſh tears of true Compunction.</p>
               <p>The Vomits are civil and religious, publick and private; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral and particular confeſſions.</p>
               <p>The Unctions are powerful and ſweet ſmelling prayers.</p>
               <p>The Minutions are Contributions to the neceſſity of the Saints.</p>
               <p>The Potions are ſelf-denyals, and bearing Chriſts Croſſe, with many the like bitter potions.</p>
               <p>The Dyets are religious faſts keeping under the Body, and bringing it into ſubjection.</p>
               <p>The Watchings are preparations againſt allurements to Sin, and the Temptations of Sathan.</p>
               <p>The Exerciſes are the practice of piety, and the conſciona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble labours of men in their Callings, Civil and Chriſtian.</p>
               <p>The Clyſters are meekneſſe, longanimity, and eaſineſſe to pardon injuries and indignities.</p>
               <p>The Cauterizings are <hi>Stigmata Jeſu,</hi> to bear in our bodies the marks of the Lord Jeſus; and all kind of perſecution for Righteouſneſſe Sake.</p>
               <p>All theſe are called and counted Soveraign remedies in their kind; and yet I muſt tell you that they are neither ſoveraign, nor remedies, any farther then they derive their virtue and energy from the <hi>Blood of Chriſt,</hi> which alone makes all our
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:93824:11"/> chriſtian endevours ſweet and acceptable to God, as God himſelf teſtifies in the 3. chap. of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> at the 17 verſe, <hi>This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed:</hi> As if he had ſaid, <hi>This,</hi> ſingularly; <hi>is,</hi> eternally; <hi>my,</hi> ſubſtantially; <hi>ſon,</hi> naturally; <hi>beloved,</hi> tranſcendently; <hi>in whom,</hi> as in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon man; I, whom it once repented that I had made man; am now well pleaſed with all men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>But we uſually judge of the goodneſſe of Phyſick by its operation, and therefore I haſten to ſpeak ſomething of that; yet that I may not make more haſt then good ſpeed, let me ſweeten your mouths after your taking this purge, with that pious ejaculation of St. <hi>Auguſtine, Inſpice vulnera Chriſti pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentis;</hi> &amp;c. Oh ſee the Wounds of Chriſt hanging on the Croſſe! the blood of him dying, the price of him redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Caput habet inclinatum in Cruce ad oſculandum,</hi> &amp;c. His head is inclined on the Croſſe to ſalute us; his arms are ſtretch'd abroad to embrace us; and his whole body is there expoſed to redeem us.</p>
               <p>And thus from the conſideration of this Phyſician, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt his Son;</hi> and his phyſick, <hi>Blood:</hi> I come now to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire how this his phyſick works; and this St. <hi>John</hi> ſhews in the very next word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>cleanſeth;</hi> It is purging Phyſick, for it <hi>cleanſeth;</hi> which is our next conſideration.</p>
               <p>The Epigrammatiſt wittily jeers a Patient that had taken ſuch Pills as did not work, <hi>Cepiſti pilulas hodiè ſed non operan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> and he tells him withall that he might ſafely take ſuch Pills on the Lords day; they would not break the Sabboth ſure, becauſe they would do no manner of work: And as it is their ſin who commonly take Phyſick on the Lords day; ſo they were juſtly puniſhed if the Phyſick ſo taken ſhould not work. But howe're bodily Phyſick ſometimes works not kindly, and ſometimes not at all, when God bleſſeth not the means becauſe we abuſe them: yet <hi>the blood of Chriſt,</hi> this Phyſick in the Text, is wondrous operative; it hath many and ſundry admirable effects, for it is <hi>Unguentum noſtrae aegrotationis</hi> (ſay the Fathers) <hi>ornamentum noſtrae conditionis, munimentum protegens contra tentationes, fulcimentum ſtabiliens in bonas operationes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:93824:11"/>
               <p>Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſtyles Chriſts blood <hi>the fountain of our election;</hi> St. <hi>Paul, the laver of regeneration;</hi> St. <hi>John, the price of our redemption:</hi> In the 12. to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> it is <hi>an Advocate to plead for us:</hi> and in the 12. of the <hi>Revelation</hi> it is a <hi>champion to fight for us;</hi> and in the 9. of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> it is a <hi>Chamberlain to open the Holy of Holies unto us:</hi> and becauſe nothing that is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther imperfect or impure ſhall ever enter there; therefore in the 13. to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> the <hi>blood of Chriſt</hi> is ſaid to make us perfect in every good work: and in my Text it purgeth us from every evil work; for here it <hi>cleanſeth us from all-Sin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yea it not only cleanſeth, but whitens too; as St. <hi>John</hi> ſhews in the 7. of the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c. They waſhed their Robes, and made them white in the blood of the Lamb.</hi> Many things are waſh'd, and waſh'd clean, which yet are not white: more then ordinary laver, and labour muſt go to white<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. And yet it is remarkable that the Saints not only waſh'd but whitened their Robes in the blood of Chriſt, there, by a Metaphor call'd the Lamb.</p>
               <p>But ſtay; doth not the Phyloſopher ſay that <hi>Quicquid ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guis attingit, inficit, &amp; foedat.</hi> What ever blood touches it pollutes, and defiles. It is true that he ſaith ſo; and he ſaith that which is true: then may not ſome Embrio in the Faith, both ſcruple and queſtion, How can blood cleanſe us, ſeeing that it pollutes all things elſe?</p>
               <p>To this hard Queſtion, the Anſwer is eaſie; for the <hi>blood of Chriſt</hi> doth not cleanſe Phyſically, but meritoriouſly: we muſt diſtinguiſh (ſay the Schoolmen) <hi>inter ſanguinem corporis Chriſti, &amp; crucis Chriſti:</hi> The blood of Chriſts body, like that which runs in our Veins, did naturally ſtain, elſe it had not been true blood: but when that true blood of his natural body was powred out on the Croſſe, and offered as a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a ſweet-ſmelling ſavour to God, for the ſins of the World; this the Apoſtle (in the firſt to the <hi>Coloſſians</hi> at the Twentieth Verſe) calls the <hi>blood of his Croſſe;</hi> and this blood of Chriſts Croſſe is of infinite merit; and this merit of his Blood, is only that, which in the Text is ſaid to <hi>cleanſe Us.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:93824:12"/>
               <p>And it <hi>cleanſeth us</hi> every way: for whereas <hi>Blood</hi> in Scripture is ſometimes put for the guilt of ſin, as in the 51. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> at the 14. Verſe, <hi>Libera me de ſanguinibus,</hi> as it is read out of the Hebrew, <hi>Deliver me from Blood-guiltineſſe, O God,</hi> &amp;c. And ſometimes for the <hi>puniſhment of Sin,</hi> as in the 27. chap. of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> at the 25. Verſe, where the Blood-ſucking and Blood-thirſty Jews cryed out, the better to encourage ſtag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gering <hi>Pilate</hi> to ſentence Chriſt to death, <hi>His blood be upon us and our Children:</hi> It is very remarkable that this <hi>Blood cleanſeth us</hi> both from the guilt of Sin, as our reconciliation; and alſo from the puniſhment of the ſame, as our ſatisfaction: In this <hi>blood</hi> note the ſingularity of the Medicine; in the extent, <hi>from all ſin,</hi> note the Univerſality of the malady; The firſt inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuates the ſole-ſufficiency of Chriſts merit; and the ſecond, the all-ſufficiency of the ſame. <hi>Haec unica medicina contra om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes morbos.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then though the <hi>Roman,</hi> like the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> Leaper, dote to this day on the <hi>Abanah</hi> and <hi>Pharphar</hi> of humane Inventions, ſuch as are their holy water, holy oyle, ſpittle, cream, ſalt, and ſundry other purging devices; yet <hi>nobis non licet eſſe tam diſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis;</hi> the holy Scripture allows us to acknowledge no other purgatory but the <hi>blood of Chriſt.</hi> This our <hi>Jordan</hi> is better then all the Rivers of their <hi>Damaſcus;</hi> which are indeed but ſo many ſtanding ponds and ſtinking puddles, compared with Chriſts Side; that one living fountain diſcovered by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zechary,</hi> which God hath ſet open on the Croſſe to <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to bath in for ſin, and for unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>And the Phyſick being thus prepared; the next thing that I am to do, is to take a ſerious view of the Patients on whom it works, and thoſe St. <hi>John</hi> here calls <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>us;</hi> we our ſelves are the Patients in the Text, for, <hi>The blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son cleanſeth us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a Queſtion much controverted in the Schools, <hi>An Chriſtus aliquid pro ſe meruerit?</hi> whether Chriſt merited any thing for himſelf? but St. <hi>John</hi> here puts it out of Queſtion, that <hi>Chriſts blood cleanſeth us;</hi> as I take it, in oppoſition, if not
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93824:12"/> excluſively to ſome others whom it doth not cleanſe; Such as are,</p>
               <p>Firſt Chriſt himſelf; Indeed God expreſly required the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitical High Prieſt to offer ſacrifice firſt for his own ſins; and then for the ſins of the people; but out Evangelical High-prieſt, Chriſt Jeſus ſacrificed himſelf, yet not for his own ſins but for the ſins of the people. He ſuffered not as a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but as a Saviour, and ſhed his <hi>blood, non ex indigentia ſui, ſed ex indulgentia noſtri.</hi> I ſay then, that Chriſts blood, doth not cleanſe himſelf; for he was conceived by the Holy Ghoſt, that is, ſay the Learned, by the manufacture, and by the operation; by the overſhadowing of the Holy Ghoſt, ſaith the <hi>Angel.</hi> He was conceived not by generation, but by benediction, ſaith <hi>Gab. Biel,</hi> and his Virgin Mother concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him, not by ſpermatical effuſion, but by the Spirit. He was begotten without carnal copulation, and brought forth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out mortal corruption; ſo that he was not leaprous in the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of nature, he was no way imaginable taincted with original Sin. And in the whole courſe of his life he was a <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> a true <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> in whom there was no guile; his converſation was as ſinleſſe, as his coat was ſeemleſſe; and being ſo free from original and actual ſin, no man could ſay unto him (as it is in the proverb, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.) <hi>Phyſician heal thy ſelf:</hi> for he had no ſickneſſe, no ſin; and conſequently his <hi>blood</hi> in the Text <hi>cleanſed</hi> not himſelf.</p>
               <p>Secondly, His <hi>blood cleanſed</hi> not the good Angels; for though they had a poſſibility to fall, yet it was never reduced into Act; and therefore they needed not the <hi>blood of Chriſt</hi> to <hi>cleanſe</hi> them <hi>from ſin,</hi> but only to confirm them in grace.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, His <hi>blood cleanſeth</hi> not the evil Angels; they are irrecoverably fallen, both becauſe they fell <hi>nullo ſuggerente,</hi> and alſo becauſe they are <hi>inveterate,</hi> and <hi>obdurate</hi> in their pride, and malice; and therefore that dangerous opinion of <hi>Origen,</hi> who held that the damned Spirits ſhall be ſaved at laſt, as it comes for ought I can ſee without any Warrant from God, ſo let it paſſe without reverence from man.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:93824:13"/>
               <p>Fourthly, The brute Beaſts as they are not capable of faith, ſo they reap no benefit by Chriſts blood-ſhed. And thus you ſee that the <hi>blood of Chriſt</hi> did not <hi>cleanſe</hi> himſelf, nor the good Angels, nor the evil Angels, nor the brute Beaſts; and if you ask, whom then? St. <hi>John</hi> anſwers flat and plain in the Text; <hi>Us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt <hi>us,</hi> and only <hi>us;</hi> for all that the Son of God incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate did, or ſaid, or ſuffered, was for us men, and our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; Chriſt was not born for himſelf, <hi>for unto</hi> Us <hi>a Child is born,</hi> ſayeth the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and <hi>unto</hi> Us <hi>a Son is given,</hi> given to <hi>Us,</hi> given for <hi>Us,</hi> He did not live for himſelf, for the Text ſaith, <hi>that he went about doing good, and hearing evil;</hi> and <hi>regium eſt audire male, cum bene feceris.</hi> Neither did he dye for himſelf; for he was <hi>ſmitten for our ſins,</hi> ſaith the ſame <hi>Iſaiah, and bruiſed for our Tranſgreſſions;</hi> The Chaſtiſement of our peace was laid upon him. And therefore being dead, juſtly was he buryed in an others Sepulchre; who dved for the ſins of others. He was a Jeſus, a Saviour, not for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf but <hi>Us:</hi> he was The Chriſt, annointed a King, a Prieſt, and a Prophet, and all and only for <hi>us;</hi> a King to protect and govern <hi>us;</hi> a Prieſt to pray, bleſſe, and offer ſacrifice for <hi>us;</hi> a Prophet to direct and inſtruct us; whoſe redemption was in his paſſion; our abſolution was in his condemnation; our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſe from the curſe was in his Croſſe; our ſatisfaction for ſin was in his ſacrifice; our cleanſing was in his blood; our morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the fleſh was in his burial; our reconciliation was in his deſcention; our newneſſe of Life was in his Reſurrection, our immortality in his conqueſt; and the fulneſſe of our joy in his Kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sic vos non vobis mellificatis apes.</hi> Thus this Maſter-Bee, made Hony not for himſelf, but <hi>Us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sic vos non vobis nidificates aves.</hi> Thus this Bird of Paradiſe, prepared his Neſt, a reſt not for himſelf, but <hi>Us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sic vos non vobis fertis aratra boves.</hi> Thus this Red Heyſer (the truth of that in the Type) bare the Yoke not for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but <hi>Us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sic vos non vobis vellera fertis oves.</hi> Thus this Lamb of God
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93824:13"/> was led to the ſlaughter, where he was not only fleic'd but flead, yet not for himſelf, but <hi>us,</hi> and <hi>us</hi> only.</p>
               <p>And as for <hi>us,</hi> and only <hi>us;</hi> ſo in the next place let me tell you, <hi>that the blood of Chriſt cleanſeth us,</hi> and <hi>us</hi> indefinitely, all of <hi>us:</hi> for St. <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt proclaims that <hi>he took away the ſins of the World,</hi> Joh. 1. 29. and leſt any ſtraight laced con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtorian Schiſmaticks ſhould reſtringe the words to their own beleiving faction, St. <hi>John</hi> (in the 2. chap. of his firſt Epiſtle General, at the 2. verſe) explains himſelf, <hi>If any man</hi> (who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever) <hi>ſin</hi> (any ſin whatſoever) <hi>we have an Advocate with the Father, even Chriſt Jeſus the Righteous, who is a propitiation for all our ſins, and not for our ſins only, but for the ſins of the whole World.</hi> And <hi>totum eſt extra quod nihil eſt.</hi> And to evince this Truth, St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the ſecond chapter of his ſecond Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> at the 15. verſe, ſaith in expreſſe tearms that <hi>Chriſt dyed for all.</hi> And in <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 9. we read that <hi>He taſted Death for every man.</hi> And in this latitude St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> took the meaning of God himſelf to be; for (gloſſing upon thoſe words of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the 10. chap. of the <hi>Acts,</hi> at the 34. Verſe) he aſſerts, <hi>Apud Deum nulla perſonarum acceptio, qui ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum excipit, ſeipſum decipit.</hi> And to the ſame effect St. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi> cryes out, devoutly as he is wont, <hi>Non horruiſti, Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, peccatricem Lachrymantem, non Chananaeam ſupplicantem, non Publicanum exorantem, non Latronem confitentem, non mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lierem in adulterio, non Davidem in homicidio, non ſedentem in telonio, non diſcipulum negantem, non diſcipulorum perſecutorem.</hi> And of this judgement in effect were all the Ancients.</p>
               <p>Then to draw all theſe ſcattered lines to their Centre, The <hi>blood</hi> of Chriſt here <hi>cleanſeth,</hi> yet neither himſelf, nor the good Angels, nor the evil Angels, nor the brute Beaſts; but <hi>us;</hi> and only <hi>Us;</hi> and all of <hi>us:</hi> and yet for cloſe of this point, I add one thing not to be omitted, <hi>viz.</hi> That as in this <hi>us,</hi> we cannot but obſerve the Communion of Saints (<hi>Omnes enim ſummi, medii, infimi, in peccato pariter nati, codem ſanguine purgati</hi>) ſo in this <hi>Nos, Us,</hi> we muſt not forget the particularity of the benefit; which all and every of <hi>us</hi> muſt apply to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, with St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the firſt chapter of his firſt Epiſtle to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93824:14"/> 
                  <hi>Timothy</hi> at the 15. Verſe, <hi>This is a faithful ſaying, and by all means worthy to be received, that Jeſus Chriſt came into the world to ſave ſinners, Quorum ego primus,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>of whom I am chief:</hi> and each of us muſt in this kind be of the <hi>Quorum.</hi> Yea every of us muſt (with St. <hi>Thomas</hi>) have the finger of his particular faith in the hole of Chriſts ſide; crying as he did, <hi>My God</hi> and <hi>my Lord,</hi> for no <hi>Deus</hi> without <hi>meus;</hi> This parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular application (ſaith <hi>Martin Luther</hi>) is <hi>ſanguis fidei;</hi> The Life-blood of Faith; This <hi>blood</hi> in the Text is Phyſick, as I told you ere while; and now I tell you again, that this, like all other Phyſick, benefits none but ſuch as take it; and they that take it muſt be ſure they keep it; for it is a purge, not a Vomit: if they caſt it up again; if they diſgeſt it not by the fervour of their devotion; yea, if they diſperſe it not, as by ſo many Veins, through the whole body of their converſation: then do they ſpill Chriſts precious <hi>blood,</hi> like water on the earth, and they ſhall be ſeverely cenſured at laſt among thoſe profeſſed Enemies of the Croſſe of Chriſt, that trampled the blood of the New Teſtament under their Feet.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>And thus from the conſideration of this Phyſician, and his Phyſick, and the operation thereof, and the Patients on whom it works; I haſten now to ſay ſomewhat of our Diſeaſe, which St. <hi>John</hi> here calls <hi>ſin;</hi> which though it be a ſhameful, painful, and loathſome Diſeaſe, yet are we not left as men, altogether without hope of help, ſince the knowledge of the Diſeaſe is the firſt ſtep to the cure; and we know what ſin is in the general; we know it to be radically all kinds of evil; a <hi>Cameleon</hi> that aſſumes the ſhape of what ever is next it; <hi>fiet enim ſubito ſus horridus, atraque Tigris, ſquammoſuſqne Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co,</hi> &amp;c. a meer Sphinx for Riddles, and impoſtures: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſin is a general notion, and <hi>Doloſus verſatur circa univerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> ſath the Phyloſopher; therefore that I might the better continue the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llegory here; and you might more diſtinctly conceive what ſin is: I preſume to call it a Sickneſſe; and that you will ſo count it in three reſpects, <hi>viz.</hi> in reſpect of the Cauſe; of the progreſſe, and of the Cure. I ſay,</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:93824:14"/>
               <p>Firſt, Sickneſſe and Sin are cauſed alike; for Phyſicians deſine ſickneſſe to be an indiſpoſition through ſome diſtemper of the body; as a Windy Cholick, or a Watry Dropſie; or a Fiery Ague, or an earthly Melancholy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And by the ſame rule, and reaſon, Divines (who are ſo many ſpiritual Phyſicians) define ſin to be an indiſpoſition through ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper of the ſoul; as the Timpany of Pride; the Leproſie of Luſt, the Lethargy of Sloth, the Dropſie of Coveteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the Surfet of Gluttony, the Conſumption of Envy, the Burning Feaver of Anger, the cold Ague Fit of Fear, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly Sickneſſe and Sin are alike in their progreſſe; for as the Lingring of any Sickneſſe inſeebles the body, and ſo infatuates the appetite, that it cannot reliſh any thing as it is in it ſelf, but as it ſeems beſt to the palate corrupted: In like manner he that goes on in the cuſtome of any ſin, doth not only weaken the powers and faculties of his Soul; but ſo inverts and perverts the right order of the ſame, that they cannot poſſibly exerciſe their due functions; and hence it comes at laſt, that the habituated ſinner doth quite loſe his ſpiritual palate, ſavouring only earthly things; he hears all that tends to his Recovery with a ſiniſter reſpect, as if (with <hi>Malchus</hi>) his right ear were cut off; he is ſenſible of nothing beyond his ſenſes, <hi>plus oculo quam oraculo credit,</hi> he muſt ſee and feel, or he will not beleive, and he underſtands not the things which belongs to his peace.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, Sickneſſe and Sin are alike in their cure; for what one way, or courſe can any Phyſician take to cure our bodily Sickneſſe; which in a qualified ſenſe, is not appliable to a Sin-ſick ſoul?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Galen</hi> (in his method <hi>Medendi</hi>) hath his <hi>Attrahentia, Repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentia, Apozemata, Alexipharmaca, Diuretica, Dia-catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo in the Goſpel (which is but a Syſtem of ſpiritual Medicaments) <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> who is our Phyſician in the Text, hath ſeveral ſorts of Phyſick, which he ſtill applies according to the quality of the perſons, which are his Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, and the inequality of their diſorders and diſeaſes. For,</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:93824:15"/>
               <p>Sometimes he uſeth Attractives, as in the 11. of St. <hi>Math. Come unto me all you, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Otherwhiles Reprocuſſives, as in the 13. of St. <hi>Luke, Tell Herod that Fox,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Sometimes Attenuatives, as in the 23. of St. <hi>Luke, Father forgive them, for they know not,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Sometimes opening Phyſick, as in tbe 16. of the <hi>Acts, when he opened the heart of Lydia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Otherwhiles he applies <hi>obſtipantia,</hi> as in the 9. of the <hi>Acts, when he ſtop'd Saul in the heat of his career, breathing out Threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Slaughter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sometimes he evacuates, as in the 20. of St. <hi>Mathew,</hi> where ſeeing his Diſciples conteſt for priority; he ſaid, <hi>Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever will be the cheif among you, let him be your Servant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Otherwhiles he reſtores, as in the 5. of St. <hi>John, Behold thou art made whole;</hi> and withal he preſcribes the convert Crip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple a dyet, <hi>Sin no more, leaſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Sometimes he adminiſters a Cordial, as in the 9. of St. <hi>Matthew, Son be of goad cheer, thy Sins be forgiven thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And where he meets with proud fleſh, to take that down, he ſometimes claps to a Coraſive; as in the 19. of St. <hi>Matthew</hi> when the youngſter gloried of his having kept the whole Law, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Then it was high time to prick the bladder, and ſo to let out the tumour; and accordingly our Phyſician cool'd his courage, <hi>Vade vende,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Go and ſell all thou haſt, and give it to the poor,</hi> &amp;c. Noe ſuch <hi>Cordolium</hi> as this; for he <hi>went away ſorrowful,</hi> ſaith the Text, <hi>for he had great poſſeſſions,</hi> and he was as unwilling to part with them as Cardinal <hi>Burboni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> profeſſed on his Death bed, that if he might have his wiſh, he would not leave his part in <hi>Paris,</hi> for a part in <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Thus <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> the Phyſician here, hath his attractive, and repercuſſive phyſick, his opening and ſtopping phyſick, his evacuating and reſtoring phyſick, his Coraſives and his Cordials. Briefly, the <hi>blood of Chriſt</hi> is meerly in, and of it ſelf, a Medicine for every malady: There is no Soul ſo woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, inflamed, exulcerated, and impoſtumated, but this
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93824:15"/> Balm of <hi>Gilead,</hi> the <hi>blood of Chriſt,</hi> can both ſupple, cleanſe, and heal it. And yet he were not only fond but frantick, who (like ſome indigent and deſperate Emperick) would try con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions upon his own ſoul; becauſe here he hath ſuch a <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licon,</hi> as, if rightly applied, will infallibly cure all diſeaſes; for though St. <hi>Johns</hi> tearm in the Text, be only in the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar number, <hi>ſin,</hi> yet it is joined with the Collective, <hi>all; (all ſin)</hi> which as the Learned well obſerve, ſignifies as much as <hi>all ſins;</hi> and ſo I am happily fallen upon the ſixth, and it is the laſt thing conſiderable in the Text, <hi>viz.</hi> The Extent and Latitude of our Sickneſſe; here neceſſarily implyed in <hi>all ſin. The blood of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Blood</hi> (in Scripture) is ſometimes uſed ſynecdochically, for the whole Paſſion of Chriſt; ſay divers of the beſt Interpreters; and that ſpeculation being elſewhere true, it may very well hold in the Text; for St. <hi>John</hi> here oppoſing <hi>Chriſts blood to all ſin,</hi> ſure his meaning is to ſhew that Chriſts ſufferings were proportionable to our ſins; for (as the moral Divines ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve) we ſinned in our firſt Parents, by caſting a wanton eye upon the forbidden fruit, and therefore Chriſt was blindfol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. They ſinned by giving ear to the Serpents ſuggeſtions, and therefore Chriſts ears were vexed with Blaſphemies and Crucifigies. They ſinned by pleaſing themſelves in the ſweet odour of the forbidden fruit, and therefore Chriſt ſuffered in <hi>Golgotha</hi> a place of ordure and ſtink. They ſinned by going to, and taking of the forbidden fruit, and therefore Chriſt was nailed to the Croſſe in his hands and feet. They ſinned by taſting of the forbidden fruit; and therefore Chriſt had Vinegar and Gall given him to drink. They ſinned by deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the forbidden fruit, and therefore Chriſt was peirced with a ſpear to the heart, which is the Fountain of Deſires. Add to this; that for our ſhameful ſins, Chriſt ſuffered a ſhameful puniſhment; for our ſtrange and unnatural ſins, Chriſt ſuffered a ſtrange and unnatural puniſhment; even a bloody ſweat in a froſty night. For our execrable and curſed ſins, Chriſt ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an execrable and curſed death; a <hi>Mors autem,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls it; even the moſt painful, ſhameful, and accurſed death
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93824:16"/> of the Croſſe; painful to his perſon, ſhameful to his office; reproachful to his eſtimation. It was <hi>mors lenta, violenta, ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guinolenta, maledicta;</hi> a death appointed by the <hi>Romans</hi> for none but ſlaves; tedeous and lingring, yet ſharp and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Briefly, our ſins as a Leproſie, had ſpred over all the parts, powers, and faculties both of ſoul and body; and Chriſts ſufferings were as general; for he paid our tranſgreſſion of every Commandement. For,</p>
               <p>We had forſaken the true God, againſt the Firſt Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement; and for this, Chriſt (as forſaken for the time of his Father) cryed out <hi>My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We had bowed the knees to Idols and Images, againſt the Second Commandement, and for this Chriſt on the Croſſe, had ſome that bowed the knee in deriſion of him.</p>
               <p>We had taken the Lords name in vain, againſt the Third Commandement, and for this Chriſts holy name was ſo uſed in vain, yea ſo blaſphemed, that his Divine works were aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to <hi>Belzebub the Prince of Devils.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We had profaned the Sabboth againſt the Fourth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement; and for this Chriſt was fettered in the bonds of <hi>Golgotha</hi> all the Sabboth long.</p>
               <p>We had diſhonoured our Father and Mother againſt the Fifth Commandement, and for this Chriſt (to whom all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is due) was villified beyond compare.</p>
               <p>We had committed Murder, againſt the Sixth Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and <hi>Chriſts blood</hi> in the Text was ſhed for it.</p>
               <p>We had committed Adultery, againſt the Seventh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, and for this, Chriſt as an unclean perſon was <hi>ſpit upon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We had ſtolen, againſt the Eighth Commandement, and Chriſt was hanged not only with, but between two Theifes for it, as if he had been the greateſt Malefactor.</p>
               <p>We had born falſe witneſſe againſt the Ninth Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Chriſt had falſe Witneſſes roſe up againſt him, which layed to his charge things that he knew not, ſaith the Pſalmiſt, prophecying of Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:93824:16"/>
               <p>We had coveted our Neighbours goods, againſt the Tenth Commandement, and Chriſt in his Paſſion ſo emptied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that there was nothing left in him to be coveted. Thus we ſinned, and thus Chriſt ſuffered, and in ſuffering ſatisfied; and ſince all ſin is either directly or reducibly againſt one or other of the Ten Commandements; St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith well in the Text, <hi>The blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son, cleanſeth us from all Sin:</hi> and ſo the whole Law of God was ſatisfied; though not <hi>rigore,</hi> in the extream rigour; yet <hi>vigore,</hi> in the full and perfect vigour thereof: Chriſt was our ſurety, and if a ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty pay the debt, the principal is diſcharged: But Chriſt in our ſtead, and for our behoof, fulfilled the Law both actively and paſſively; for firſt, by his active obedience he did for us all that we ſhould do; and then by his paſſive obedience he ſuffered for us, all that we ſhould ſuffer, and ſo much St. <hi>Iohn</hi> inſinuates here, where he aſſures us, for our unſpeakable comfort, that <hi>The blood of Jeſus,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Yea it is worth noting that Chriſt ſhed his blood ſeven ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral times, on purpoſe (as it may be conceived) to cleanſe us from thoſe ſeven, which are commonly called deadly Sins: For</p>
               <p>Firſt, In his Circumciſion he bled, to cleanſe us from the impurity of Luſt, which is predominant in that part.</p>
               <p>Secondly, In his Agony in the Garden, he was caſt into a bloody Sweat, that ſo he might breath out our ill humours contracted by Gluttony.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, In his Flagellation, when he was whipped, he bled, to cleanſe us from Envy, the cruelleſt ſcourge in the World: <hi>Invidia ſiculi non invenere Tyranni majus tormentum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, In his Coronation, when they crowned him with Thorns, he bled, to aſwage our pride: then let not us crown our heads with Roſe-buds, ſince Chriſt for our Sakes was crowned with Thorns, ingenious malice, crown to delude him, Thorns to torment him.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, In his Crucifiction, when they nailed his hands to the Croſſe, he bled, to cleanſe us from Covetouſneſſe: and as (<hi>Albertus Magnus</hi> well obſerves) his hands were then exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:93824:17"/> open, and perforated, and conſequently could not then retain any thing, to teach us that (if God hath enabled us, we muſt give (as he hath commanded) liberally, totally univerſally.</p>
               <p>Sixthly, In his Crucifiction, when they alſo nailed his feet to the Croſſe, he bled; to cleanſe us from the Scurvy of Idleneſſe, and ſo to quicken our pace in the Paths of Gods Commandements.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, when the Souldier peirced his ſide with a ſpear, he bled, to give vent to our anger. The Phyloſopher in his firſt Book <hi>De Anima,</hi> calls Anger the Boyling of the Blood about the Heart, and accordingly St. <hi>John</hi> appoſitely notes (<hi>John</hi> 19. 34.) that aſſoon as Chriſts ſide was opened, there forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with iſſued out of the wound, <hi>both water and blood,</hi> the two Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and Seals of the New Teſtament, ſaith <hi>Gregory Nyſſen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Exiit aqua</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Hierome) ad abluendum fideles, ſanguis ad damnandum incredulos.</hi> There came out Water for our ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and Blood for our abſolution.</p>
               <p>Water (ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtome) ut <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to renſe us,</hi> and blood <hi>ut <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to redeem us,</hi> for without blood there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
               <p>Water to cleanſe us from original Guiltineſſe; and Blood to waſh away our actual filthineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ex aqua frigida, &amp; ſanguine calido, aegrotis balneum tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peravit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gaſpar Melo:</hi> of cold water, and warm blood, our great Phyſician in the Text, tempered an excellent bath for his ſin-ſick-patients: Water to cool our inordinate fervour in the purſuit of all earthly things, and Blood to inflame our hearts with the love of the heavenly. Briefly,</p>
               <p>That Water and Blood ſhewed a right noble temper in him, and withal they teach <hi>us,</hi> that if we ſincerely deſire <hi>Chriſts blood</hi> ſhould effectually <hi>cleanſe us,</hi> then we muſt with the men of <hi>Mizpeh,</hi> draw water too; we muſt do our endevour tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughly to waſh our ſouls in penitential tears, from all thoſe ſins which Chriſt hath purged away by the merit of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. He that at firſt made <hi>us,</hi> without <hi>us,</hi> will not at laſt,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:93824:17"/> ſave <hi>us,</hi> without <hi>us:</hi> for to his merit we muſt joyn our ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour: This Phyſick in the Text never works more kindly, then when it is applyed by the faithful with ſome of their own Eye-bright Water.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Moſes</hi> at his departure out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> would not leave to <hi>Pharaoh, ne ungulum quidem,</hi> not ſo much as an hoof: and ſhall Chriſt be leſſe faithful, leſſe powerful, then his ſervant <hi>Moſes?</hi> It cannot be, and therefore ſure he will not leave the hoof of any one ſinful affection in the ſoul, which he <hi>cleanſeth</hi> with his <hi>blood:</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> here witneſſes that he <hi>cleanſeth us from all ſin:</hi> whether it be original or actual ſin, mortal or venial ſin, ſin of omiſſion or commiſſion, ſin of ignorance or knowledge, ſin of weakneſſe or wilfulneſſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as there is no ſin ſo ſmall, but the pure eyes of God the Father can ſee it, ſo I will be bold to ſay, that there is no ſin ſo great, but the pure <hi>blood</hi> of God the Son can <hi>cleanſe us</hi> from it: for <hi>The blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son, cleanſeth us from all ſin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it makes very well for the peace of the Church, that this univerſal particle <hi>All,</hi> is here expreſſed, it may be uſeful at this day.</p>
               <p>Firſt, againſt all ſuch Conſiſtorian Schiſmatiques, who (as if they were of Gods Cabinet counſel) do ſo perempto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily preach, and preſſe a fatal, and inevitable decree of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation; whereby they drive many a poor ſoul into deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair, for which Chriſt dyed, and damne ſo many of their Congregation, as are not of their faction: fain would I know of theſe Sons of Thunder, whether they believe the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Diſciple St. <hi>John,</hi> who was both an Evangeliſt, a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, and an Apoſtle? (in his Goſpel an Evangeliſt, in his Apocalyps a Prophet, and in his Epiſtles an Apoſtle) if they dare ſay, they believe him not, then have they both a Prophet, an Evangeliſt, and an Apoſtle in the Text, in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe tearms refuting them; for he ſaith, that the <hi>blood of Chriſt cleanſeth us from all ſin;</hi> and if ſo, then there is no mans caſe whatſoever ſo deſperate, but if he take this ſpiritual <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicon</hi> it will cure him.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:93824:18"/>
               <p>Secondly, This Collective, <hi>All,</hi> is comfortable againſt the Enormity of Sin, for if Chriſts blood cleanſes us from all ſin, then there is no ſin whatſoever, in its own nature unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable: and if any ſhall object that our Saviour (ſpeaking of the ſin againſt the Holy-Ghoſt, in the 12. of St. <hi>Matthew</hi>) ſaith <hi>it ſhall never be forgiven, neither in this World, nor in the World to come!</hi> I anſwer with the Ancients, that this impoſſibility of pardon, is not <hi>exparte gratiae Divinae,</hi> but <hi>pervicaciae huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, proculcantis ſanguinem Jeſu, &amp; ſanari renuentis.</hi> When <hi>Cain</hi> had murthered his Brother <hi>Ibel</hi> (who was both a Virgin, and a Martyr, and a Type of Chriſt) in the conſciouſneſſe of ſo horrid a fact, he cryed out, <hi>My ſin is greater then can be forgiven:</hi> but St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> in an holy impatience, was ſo tranſported with the conſideration of <hi>Cains</hi> deſperate conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; that he gave him the Lye; <hi>Mentiris Cain;</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Cain</hi> thou lyeſt, thy ſin is not greater then can be forgiven; for God wants not mercy enough to forgive thee, hadſt thou but grace enough to beg forgiveneſſe. If thou periſh it is thy own fault; who by wilfully rejecting the Medicine that ſhould heal thee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> doſt obſtruct thy own mercies.</p>
               <p>The Apoſtle ſpeaking of all obſtinate, obdurate, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent ſinners, calls them <hi>Veſſels of diſhonour;</hi> and it is with them, as with an empty veſſel caſt into the Sea; where though there be water enough to fill it; yet it ſtill remains empty, becauſe it hath not a capacity for want of a vent, or hole to take the water in at.</p>
               <p>Thirdly this Collective, <hi>All;</hi> plainly diſcovers that there is no need at all of humane purgations, and ſatisfactions; <hi>for if Chriſts blood cleanſeth us from all ſinne;</hi> then there is nothing left for Maſſes, Diriges, Trentals, purgatory, and the like goulden-tail'd doctrines, to do; and by conſequence down falls the Dagon of <hi>Popiſh</hi> puppets, and the trinkets of their indulgence-mongers, which like ſo many <hi>Laplanders,</hi> do in truth ſell nothing but winde: The <hi>Pope</hi> ſends them forth for filthy lucres Sake, to make merchandiſe of mens ſouls.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, this Collective, <hi>All;</hi> refells and refutes the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous errour of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and <hi>Novatians; qui negarunt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:93824:18"/> lapſis paenitenti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m, &amp; ſalutem: for if Chriſts blood cleanſeth from all Sin,</hi> then without queſtion thoſe ſinnes are neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly included, which men commit after regeneration, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion. The good <hi>Samaritan,</hi> I mean this Phyſician in the Text, doth not deal with our ſins, as the unjuſt Steward in the Goſpel, did with his ſumms; when the bill is an hundred, to ſet down fifty; for we are not ſolvant; even fifty would as utterly undo us, as if they were ten thouſand talents. St. <hi>John</hi> here ſpeaks fully, ſaithfully, and ſatisfactorily to all troubled, and trembling conſciences, <hi>The blood of Jeſus Chriſt, his Son, cleanſeth us from all Sin:</hi> yet take heed that out of theſe ſweet, and ſaving premiſſes, you draw not a fond, and falſe concluſion; They that preſume to ſinne, becauſe h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re they have ſuch a ſalve as will cure all ſores, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a ſpe fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Bernard, ſperando percunt.</hi> They are not Bees, but of a Spider like nature, who ſuck that poyſon, out of theſe ſaving flowers: That one dead Flie, is enough to infect this whole box of ſo precious ointment. Shall we Sin, and Sin, (heaping <hi>Peleon</hi> upon <hi>Oſſa</hi>) that grace may abound? God forbid, ſaith St. <hi>Paul. Rom.</hi> 6. 2. There's no reaſon (ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>) that Man ſhould be the worſe, becauſe God is better.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>
                  <hi>Martials</hi> Flie play'd ſo long under a tree, till at laſt it was wrapt in Amber; and ſo congeal'd in the drops, that fell from the boughs; <hi>Sic modo quae f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap> vita contempta manente, funeribus facta eſt nunc pretioſa ſuis.</hi> I cloſe with the moral, The beſt men on earth are but wormes, ſaith the Princely Prophet in the 22 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> at the ſixt, and we ſee by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, that ſome kind of worms do turn Flies: then let us who are but worms by nature; learn, by grace, to imitate his Flie: let us, Oh let us be ever hovering about the tree of Chriſt's Croſſe; till we be wrapt, and embalm'd and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomb'd in the precious amber of his freſh-bleeding wounds; who (as our Phyſician) bled himſelf to death, that we his Sin ſick patients might live, the life of grace here; and the life of glory in the Heavens: and this he grant us, who hath ſo dearly bought us, even Jeſus Chriſt the righteous. To
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:93824:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> whom with God the Father, and the thrice bleſſed Spirit, be aſcrib'd (as moſt due is) all glory, power, and praiſe, now and for ever.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Sermons and other Peices of Divinity, Printed and Sold by <hi>JOHN PLAYFORD</hi> at his Shop in the <hi>Temple.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THE Great Work of Redemption;</hi> Delivered in four Excellent <hi>Sermons,</hi> Preached at <hi>St. Pauls,</hi> and at the <hi>Spittle,</hi> in the year 1641. Firſt by Dr. <hi>Soames</hi> on <hi>Good Friday;</hi> Second by Biſhop <hi>Morton</hi> on <hi>Eaſter Day;</hi> the Third by Dr. <hi>Potter,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Carlile,</hi> on <hi>Eaſter Munday;</hi> Fourth by <hi>Dr. Weſtfield</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Briſtol,</hi> on <hi>Eaſter Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>St. <hi>Pauls Thanksgiving;</hi> A <hi>Sermon</hi> Preached in the <hi>Abby Church</hi> of <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> before the Houſe of Peers, By <hi>James Buck</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Sermon</hi> Preached on the 30. Day of <hi>January</hi> (being the Day on which his Sacred Majeſty King <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt was murdered) the Text <hi>Lam. 4. 20.</hi> By <hi>John King</hi> Dean of <hi>Tuam</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Martyrdome of King</hi> Charles <hi>the Firſt,</hi> or his Conformity with <hi>Chriſt</hi> in his Sufferings; In a <hi>Sermon</hi> Preached at <hi>Bredah,</hi> before his Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Majeſty King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second; By the Right Reverend <hi>John</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Down.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſiderations touching the Liturgy of the Church of</hi> England. In Reference to his Majeſties late Gracious Declaration concerning the ſame; By the Right Reverend <hi>John Gauden</hi> D. D. and now Lord Biſhop of <hi>Exeter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Souls Life,</hi> or <hi>Pious Meditations for Devout Chriſtians;</hi> Written by the Religious and Harmonious <hi>Richard Portman,</hi> Cheif Organiſt of His Late Majeſties Royal Chappel; to which is added his Pious Meditation on the Divine uſe of <hi>Muſick.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
